Xiaoqin Feng (冯小琴)

Curriculum Vitae

fengxqinx@gmail.com

Online version: https://xqfeng-josie.github.io/resume/cv

Last updated: March 12, 2023

Google Scholar **(1)**

XqFeng-Josie 🜎

Introduction

I am currently a Senior Speech Algorithm Engineer at Mobvoi AI Lab, with a working focus on text-to-speech (TTS). Specifically, my area of expertise is in <u>text information extraction</u> based on cross- and multi-lingual aspects. My research interests lie in <u>natural language processing(NLP)</u>, with a particular emphasis on natural language understanding, semantic analysis, knowledge acquisition, information extraction, information representation, robust learning, data mining, and their practical application.

EDUCATION

Master Student Software Engineer (M.Sc.)

Oct. 2016 - Jan. 2019

Beijing University of Technology BJUT; overall grade: 86 (max. 100) between "Very Good" and "Good"

Beijing, China

Bachelor Student Computer Science (B.Eng.)

Sep. 2012 - Jul. 2016

Southwest Minzu University SMU; overall grade: 3.66 (max. 4.0), "Top 5" of 154 students

Chengdu, China

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Speech algorithm Engineer

Jul. 2019 - Present

[Mobvoi] [出门问问开放平台]

Beijing, China

- As mentor: working with 3 interns (annual) in NLP and Text-to-speech(TTS)
- As researcher: tokenization, text normalization, polyphone, prosody, stress, spoken events, speaking style, emotion, unified-model.(text information extraction)
- As developer: develop and optimize algorithms of TTS and NLP, online and portable server to support toB/toC services.
- **Involved techniques**: *Language*: C/C++, Python, Bash; *Knowledge*: data mining, semantic analysis, contrastive learning, knowledge distillation, pre-training, multi-task; semi-supervision;

Tools: Linux, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Redis, MySQL, Docker, gRPC, XML etc.

• **Key results**: tech-website: VoiceMaker, DupDub; (*)regular staff opportunity; one co-author submission to *PRML 2022*; one first-author submission to *INTERSPEECH 2023* + 9 patents.

Algorithm Research(Intern)

Aug. 2018 - Dec. 2018

TAL AI Lab

Beijing, China

- · As researcher: knowledge tracing: network representation learning(NE/NRL), relation information(co- with Dr.Wang)
- As developer: develop a deep knowledge tracing(DKT) pipeline to verify different methods: data mining, weight graph building, graph embedding, metric distance
- Involved techniques: *Language*: Python, Bash; *Knowledge*: data mining, graph embedding, LSTM, GCN etc.; *Tools*: TensorFlow, AliCloud, Google Codelab, t-SNE, etc.
- Key results: Outstanding Intern of 10 members; one co-author submission to AIED2019; (*) regular staff opportunity

DeeCamp AI Lab (Member)

Jun. 2018 - Aug. 2018

 $Dee Camp-co\ with\ Peking\ University\ \&\ Sinovation\ Ventures$

Beijing, China

- $\circ~$ As researcher: Movie Recommendation based on knowledge graph (KG) (co- with two Ph.D. & three M.Sc.)
- · As developer: data mining, knowledge graph building, verify RS methods(CF, FM, PNN, etc.), API
- Involved techniques: *Language*: Python, Bash, JavaScript; *Tools*: Keras, Ucloud, Google Codelab, etc.
- Key results: github project, Excellent Team of 20 groups, (*)internship opportunity

Ali Tianchi Competition (Competitor)

Sep. 2017 - Dec. 2017

Bwijing, China

Tianchi - co- with CCF

- Subject: User Location Prediction: predicting user's current store location based on user consumption data.
- As researcher: data mining, boosting learning, ensemble learning, ablation analysis

- Involved techniques: *Language*: Python, Bash, SQL; *Knowledge*: data mining, random forest(RF), LR, XgBoost, GBDT, LightGBM, etc.; *Tools*: MySQL, AliCloud, etc.
- Key results: Primary: 52/2845 , Final: 19/2845

Personal Projects Sep. 2016 - Aug. 2018

IOT-Lab Beijing, China

- o Ali Tianchi Competition: O2O coupon usage predictions e.g.
- - TextCNN: Methods are implemented based on TF-IDF, xgboost, lgb, textcnn, etc. code
- - Dialogue Generation: Simmc2 task: Methods are implemented based on BERT, GPT, Multimodal, etc.
- · TAL AI Lab: FutrueCamp: Research on Recommendation Systems, after that I got an internship
- IoT Bus HD Intelligent Video Surveillance: Programming and development of application algorithms
- - IOT-AI Video Analyser: Programming and development of application algorithms

EXPERTISE AND SKILLS

Expertise is context- and comparison-dependent. Here states the years of experience in terms of use, also indicates a subjective estimation of the level of expertise (either elementary, intermediate, experienced, or expert):

- NLP/Speech Syntheis: Semantic Analysis (tokenization, text normolization, polyphone, g2p, prosody, unified-frontend, spoken events experienced); Emotion Analysis (speaking style, stress, emotion analysis, contrastive learning experienced); Knowledge Information (knowledge tracking, knowledge representation, etc. intermediate); TTS Backend Model (acoustic models, vocoder elementary);
- Programming: Data Mining (5 years of study and work, numpy/pandas/seaborn/t-sne/etc., experienced); Backend Development (4 years of industrial c++ server engineering, good at logic/structure, using C++/Python/etc., experienced).
- Language: C/C++ (4+ years, experienced); Python (5+ years, experienced); Writing (4+years, good writing habits.) I speak native Mandarin; elementary English.

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

Ali Tianchi Competition Good,19/2845	Sep. 2018 <i>Beijing, China</i>
National Scholarship Southwest Minzu University	Sep. 2016 Chengdu, China
Outstanding Secretary of the Youth League Scholarship Southwest Minzu University	May 2014 Chengdu, China
Annual Excellent Student Innovative Project Southwest Minzu University, 2nd Award	Sep. 2013 Chengdu, China
Outstanding Student Scholarship Southwest Minzu University	Jun. 2013,Jun. 2014 Chengdu, China
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	

Lecture - Embedded System Design Practice

2018 Winter

As teaching assistant at BJUT, for M.Sc. students, approx. 80 students each year.

Company - Speech & NLP

2021-present

Annual As a mentor at Mobvoi, for interns (students), annual. 3 students.

Publications

Proceedings

- Feng X, Xie R, Sheng J, et al. Population statistics algorithm based on MobileNet. Journal of Physics: Conference Series. IOP Publishing, 2019(ICSP'19), 6 pages. https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1742-6596/1237/2/022045/pdf.
- Wang Z, <u>Feng X</u>, Tang J, et al. *Deep Knowledge Tracing with Side Information*. International conference on artificial intelligence in education.
 Springer, Cham, 2019(AIED'19), 5 pages. https://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.00372.pdf.
- Rong Xie, Feng X A method of quick edge detection based on Zynq. International Conference on Cloud Computing and Internet of Things, 2018(CCIOT'18), 5 pages. CCIOT'2018
- Sheng J, Feng X Research on the Internet of Things Platform for Smart and Environmental Protection. International Conference on Cloud Computing and Intelligence Systems, 2018(CCIS'18), 5 pages. CCIS'2018
- Zhang J, Feng X, Chen Y, et al. *Prosody Prediction With Discriminative Representation Method.* International Conference on Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning, 2022(PRML'22), 5 pages PRML'2022
- Chi W, Feng X(*euqal contribution), Chen Y, et al. Multi-granularity Semantic and Acoustic Stress Prediction for Expressive TTS. Conference of the International Speech Communication Association, 2023(INTERSPEECH'23), 5 pages. reviewing.

Patents

- FENG XIAOQIN, et al.. Polyphone labeling method and device, and computer readable storage medium. Mobvoi(algorithm),2019,CN111078898A
- FENG XIAOQIN et al. Speech synthesis method and device and computer readable storage medium. Mobvoi(algorithm),2020,CN110970013A
- FENG XIAOQIN, et al. Polyphone labeling method and device, and computer readable storage medium. Mobvoi(application),2020,CN111145724A
- FENG XIAOQIN, et al. Construction method and device of rhythm model, rhythm labeling method and electronic equipment. Mobvoi(algorithm),2022,CN115470351A
- FENG XIAOQIN, et al. Construction method and device of rhythm model, rhythm labeling method and electronic equipment. Mobvoi(algorithm),2022,CN115470350A
- FENG XIAOQIN, et al. Voice synthesis method and device, electronic equipment and storage medium. Mobvoi(algorithm),2022,CN115547289A
- other 3 co-patents: CN111079428A CN111178042A CN115578998A

Theses

- Xiaoqin Feng. 2019. Research on multi-scene video intelligent processing system and scheduling management algorithm. In the Institute of Software Engineering. Beijing University of Technology. 78 pages. Master Thesis. https://kns.cnki.net/master_thesis.pdf
- Xiaoqin Feng. 2016. *Intelligent Laboratory Management System*. In the Institute of Computer Science and Engineering. Southwest Minzu University. 37 pages. **Bachelor Thesis**.